<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nosce te, (humors.) By Richard Turner</title>
            <author>Turner, Richard, poet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118702</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853909</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19311</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14041)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19311)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1012:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nosce te, (humors.) By Richard Turner</title>
                  <author>Turner, Richard, poet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] W[indet] for Iefferey Chorlton, and are to be sold at his shop, at the great north doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Epigrams.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Epigrams, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:1"/>
            <p>NOSCE TE, <hi>(HVMORS.)</hi>BY RICHARD TVRNER.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Diſce dediſcere.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device formerly of John Wolfe; framed device of a fleur-de-lis with two cherubs and I. W. (McKerrow 294)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by I. W. for <hi>Iefferey Chorlton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the great North doore of Pauls. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ignare indignis</hi> (Reader) ſoft, I might as wel haue called you gentle, <hi>per Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſin,</hi> you'l ſay but you were not beſt bee prating, leſt I make <hi>Cato</hi> claw you by the Coxecombe, with <hi>ne ad concilium, &amp;c.</hi> But Apology, define <hi>plura,</hi> doe you heare <hi>(predicte)</hi> heeres aſixepenie purchaſe for you; I thinke you may call it <hi>Epigrames,</hi> or a booke of this thing and that thing, and iuſt nothing, if you haue better skil, you may ſcoffe at it, or you may looke and laugh at it, you may buy it and beare it, and then you may eyther reade it, or heare it, or elſe take it and teare it, or if you can doe nothing elſe, clip your taile twixt your legs, like a weary ſheepe, and cry mew but may be, your ſtomacke hath preſt your belly to the three peny Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, take this word in your pocket, for tis not there I aſsure you. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_misinterpreting_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:3"/>
            <head>TO THE CARPING <hi>Miſinterpretor.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>CEaſe gualde-backt-guilt, my inſcious lines to mince,</l>
            <l>The world will know you are rub'd if once you wince,</l>
            <l>They hemme within their ſeeming criticke wall,</l>
            <l>Particularly none, generally all;</l>
            <l>Mongſt which if you haue chancht to catch a pricke</l>
            <l>Crie Wee-hie if you will, but do not kicke.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:3"/>
            <head>NOSCE TE, (Humors.)</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>NOſce te, (Humors)</hi> fantaſticke, know thy ſelfe,</l>
               <l>The ape of faſhions, Natures very Elfe,</l>
               <l>Here learne, abhorre, reforme thy infamous rumors,</l>
               <l>Platter fac't <hi>Proteus (Noſce te, Humors.)</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>MEete ſwearing <hi>Samme;</hi> and ſay you are glad he's wel,</l>
               <l>Euen ſo is he by you; he is by hell:</l>
               <l>Aske him if he a pinte of wine will take,</l>
               <l>He'le giue it you; aye by the Stygian lake:</l>
               <l>Tell him t'is ſpoke his dealings are but euill,</l>
               <l>His humor ſcorneth rumor, aye by the diuell.</l>
               <l>This his deteſted ſwearing, each man loathes,</l>
               <l>His oathes are his, God grant, he not his oathes.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>SEarch from the orient to the occident</l>
               <l>To find ſome vnknowne-land by accedent:</l>
               <l>Wring <hi>Preſter Iohn</hi> by the beard, draw <hi>Cham</hi> by'th heeles,</l>
               <l>Tie ſuch as <hi>Hector</hi> to our chariot wheeles,</l>
               <l>Piſh, what were this? now none are famde but drinkers;</l>
               <l>Lets to a tauerne, be as drunke as Tinkers,</l>
               <l>Drag vp ſome whores into the roome by'th'haire,</l>
               <l>Swingde vp the Vintner, throw the Drawer down ſtaires,</l>
               <l>Rouſe out with ſuch a horrid thunder, ſcore.</l>
               <l>Make <hi>Errabus</hi> amaſde, the <hi>Welkin</hi> rore,</l>
               <l>Fall out, ſcolde, fight, and after all theſe quarrels,</l>
               <l>Sucke out the very entrals of the barrels:</l>
               <l>O had we neuer ended Spaniſh iarres,</l>
               <l>Then theſe had neuer beene our Engliſh warres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>OTher mens ioyes chifefly from thoſe <hi>Ioiſe</hi> deſcend,</l>
               <l>Yet (cruel <hi>Ioiſe</hi>) my ioyes in <hi>Ioiſe</hi> haue end,</l>
               <l>My onely ioyes, by onely <hi>Ioiſe</hi> are croſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioiſe</hi> is my loue, in whome my ioyes are loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>HArke how he blowes, puffe, he'l caſſear you all</l>
               <l>Gallants, alane, giue <hi>Gurmandiſe</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all:</l>
               <l>O Buttockes! bigger then a paire of butt's,</l>
               <l>The very paragon of greaſe and guts,</l>
               <l>Atturney, I crie you mercy, now Ile ſweare</l>
               <l>Tis he hath made tuftaffatie ſo deare,</l>
               <l>A ſixeyearde iacket's nothing, for ile tell ye</l>
               <l>Th'ers a huge circuit bout his boundles belly;</l>
               <l>Ale by whole runnes, the vaſtiles conceales,</l>
               <l>Tis ſtrange, no tripe-wife for his garbage deales,</l>
               <l>Yet all's not loſt by feeding <hi>Gurmandiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then weepe not <hi>(Beſſe)</hi> for when thy husband dies,</l>
               <l>Doe thou but ſeeth the entrals of the chuffe,</l>
               <l>Thou art worth at leaſt fiue marke in kitching ſtuffe;</l>
               <l>Yet ſoft, ile make a Proclamation,</l>
               <l>That cloth and ſtuffe, may ioine in ſupplication;</l>
               <l>And pray (O mutton paſties) gooſe and pigge,</l>
               <l>That bellies may breake before they grow ſo bigge.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>BLeſſed Creator) turne thy curſed creature,</l>
               <l>The beſt by name's become the badſt by nature</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grace,</hi> now giue ore that name, be <hi>Grace</hi> no more</l>
               <l>O <hi>Grace</hi> is graceles, for <hi>Grace</hi> is a whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SHine hollow Caues, and thou celeſtiall round,</l>
               <l>Droppe downe harmonious accents from thy ſphears,</l>
               <l>Let heaven and earth with merry noiſe reſound,</l>
               <l>The Flagge hanges out to day thei'l baite the beares,</l>
               <l>For how to ſpend my time I could not tell,</l>
               <l>Cauſe al the whores of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> be in <hi>Bridewel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus idle Libertines conſume their liues,</l>
               <l>In ſome deteſted ſinne, ſome horrid vice,</l>
               <l>Rauiſhing maides, diſhoneſting mens wiues.</l>
               <l>At tauernes, bawdy houſes, playes, whores, dice,</l>
               <l>They that haue libertie, do thus abuſe it,</l>
               <l>Curſed, nay all moſt dambd, are they that vſe it.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>MVmme chancing <hi>Tom</hi> to his eternall grace,</l>
               <l>The dicing-heraldes did create ſiſe ace,</l>
               <l>This <hi>Tom</hi> in gamling was (forſooth) ſo nice</l>
               <l>No tricke eſcapte his knowledge on the dice:</l>
               <l>Barde cater trayes, fullomes, high cuts, low cuts</l>
               <l>Nay <hi>Tom</hi> did know the dices very guts,</l>
               <l>But what auaileth skill, if lucke be bad,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingratum fatum, Tom</hi> loſt all he had.</l>
               <l>When loe to dire reuenge <hi>Thomas</hi> is drawne,</l>
               <l>And put his cloake (deſpight the dice) to pawne,</l>
               <l>But valiant dice better at blowes then brawle</l>
               <l>Conquerde at armes, cloke, doublet, hoſe and all,</l>
               <l>Quoth furious <hi>Tom,</hi> is this my merit's meede?</l>
               <l>A plague vpon't, heer's bare—lucke indeed</l>
               <l>Then cals all villanes, rogues, panders and whores,</l>
               <l>And in his ſummer's ſute, ſwinges out of dores,</l>
               <l>Catch-poles, and bruers horſes, giue the wall,</l>
               <l>Or breechles <hi>Thomas</hi> ſweares hee'l bang you all.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MEndoſo's</hi> turnd, what? ſwaggerer, by this light,</l>
               <l>I am ſure he is not, beleaue't he is, hee'l fight,</l>
               <l>Hee's rich and valiant, as a man may be,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>London</hi> affordes none properer then he,</l>
               <l>See how he laughes, nay, prethee doe not ſcore it,</l>
               <l>I am ſure tis true, I heard him when he ſwore it,</l>
               <l>Truſt me you wrong the Gentleman, nay fie,</l>
               <l>Tis a leſt indeed, <hi>Mendoſo ſweare and lie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Gentleman, why? he hath beene once or twiſe</l>
               <l>Why, I hope to God a Seruing man may riſe,</l>
               <l>Why name you <hi>Ambodexter</hi> mongſt the reſt,</l>
               <l>Did he follow him? tis true, he did in ieſt,</l>
               <l>The other morning to diſgeſt his canne,</l>
               <l>To cut <hi>Tobacco,</hi> he ſwore he miſt his man,</l>
               <l>Diſgrac't to fil't himſelfe, in a great rage</l>
               <l>Can curſe the Earle, that needes would haue his Page,</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>He had a Page, he lies that dare ſay nay,</l>
               <l>Three daies he ſeru'd him, ere he runne away:</l>
               <l>He's turnd I aſſure you, lies as well as many,</l>
               <l>Bids God renounce his ſoule better than any:</l>
               <l>Cries (villaines) I haue learnd a new Carouſe,</l>
               <l>No man comes neere me in a Bawdie houſe:</l>
               <l>When others pawnd their land, he ſpent no ground,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he had none: but almoſt three hundred pound.</l>
               <l>He ſpent indeed a little which he got,</l>
               <l>Queſtion not how, perchance it was his lot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>AS my yong Miſtris walked by her gate,</l>
               <l>A Beggar askt her worſhip for a pennie,</l>
               <l>Shee prizing worſhip at the loweſt rate,</l>
               <l>Bade him be packing for he gote not any:</l>
               <l>Another kneeling, came with (good your honor)</l>
               <l>And t'was no maruell, for ſhee wore a Hood:</l>
               <l>Shee hearing ſuch a title put vpon her,</l>
               <l>I warrant (quoth ſhee) his breeding hath bin good:</l>
               <l>Out came her purſe, and money, read how much,</l>
               <l>A penny faith, her honors bounty was ſuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>TOuch not my Rapier, for by my rapiers hilt,</l>
               <l>If thou defile my rapier with thy ſight,</l>
               <l>Then by the radiance of my rapiers gilt,</l>
               <l>My rapier ſends you to eternall night:</l>
               <l>But ſee it quoth a? know ſlaue, my rapier ſcornes</l>
               <l>The vile beholding of ſo baſe a groome.</l>
               <l>What will you faith? come, come, Ile cut your cornes:</l>
               <l>Die (villaine) die, or quickly leaue the roome,</l>
               <l>Cham not ſo ſimple, quoth the countrey clowne,</l>
               <l>To runne away for euery Mouſe that cries.</l>
               <l>Chau beene the luſtieſt man in all our town:</l>
               <l>Quoth Hot-ſpurre (O my ſpleene) by <hi>Ioue</hi> he dies.</l>
               <l>Plain-dealing <hi>Tom,</hi> eſteeming that courſe beſt,</l>
               <l>Drew a hudge Ale-houſe dagger from his backe:</l>
               <l>Put vp, quoth Hot-ſpurre, canſt abide no ieſt,</l>
               <l>In conſcience I ſhould beate thee like a ſacke:</l>
               <l>Ruſticke was ready, Hot-ſpurre gan to fawne,</l>
               <l>Faith hee'd haue beate him, if he had not drawne.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>OBtaine of me my liuing, lands and life,</l>
               <l>Obtaine the nightly lodging with my wife:</l>
               <l>Commaund me hang my ſelfe, nay fight for thee,</l>
               <l>Nay (ſweet friend) my rapier muſt be free</l>
               <l>What elſe I haue, by your name is knowne,</l>
               <l>What's mine's my friende's, ſaue only that's mine owne:</l>
               <l>Of mettels ſtrange, of compoſition rare,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Mars</hi> his ſword, my rapier ſcornes compare,</l>
               <l>Is not poſſeſſion to thefts fier fuel?</l>
               <l>Whoe'd truſt ſecurity ſuch a iewel?</l>
               <l>Who hath your rapier that you doe not feare it?</l>
               <l>Nay, where's your rapier that you do not weare it?</l>
               <l>O ſir, ſo many cans of expence,</l>
               <l>Why doe you laugh? faith tis not pawnd for ſixpence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SPlendor of nature, luſter of a noſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe colour far exceeds the reddeſt roſe,</l>
               <l>A radiant noſe, for brightnes glorious,</l>
               <l>A noſe whoſe greatnes is notorious,</l>
               <l>All moderne noſes this noſe farre out goes,</l>
               <l>A handfull brode, why tis monſtrous for a noſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Miroſos</hi> comming to a tauerne neere,</l>
               <l>In gallant tearmes began to curſe and ſweare,</l>
               <l>This roguiſh houſe, what the poxe brought me hither,</l>
               <l>What are theſe rogues and whores gone altogether:</l>
               <l>Tis a maingie houſe, here gentlemen may ſtarue,</l>
               <l>Whilſt knaues and drabs are playing that ſhould ſerue:</l>
               <l>Anone ſaies one, may it pleaſe your worſhip dine,</l>
               <l>My leaſure is (you ſlaue) to drinke ſome wine.</l>
               <l>What ſmell is this? faugh, here is a filthy fogge,</l>
               <l>A ſhaking roome, able to choke a dogge:</l>
               <l>Such durty towels, rude cuſhions, rotten ſtooles,</l>
               <l>Plague on ſuch Beggar-maſters, and men fooles.</l>
               <l>A quart of <hi>Ipocras</hi> freſh, neat, and pure,</l>
               <l>Now by my bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, I ſhall be angrie ſure:</l>
               <l>The boy with humble flexure doth decline,</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dging to the Celler downe for wine,</l>
               <l>Meane while <hi>Miroſo's</hi> gone, and wot you why?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oxe take the Beaker, muſt he ſtand ſo nie.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>I Haue a loue by whom the morning riſe</l>
               <l>Lookes ſtill to haue her bluſhing glory tainted,</l>
               <l>Were they not bleard, O ſhee had excellent eies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The world affoards a face no better painted:</l>
               <l>A lippe like to <hi>Diana,</hi> her fountaines brincke,</l>
               <l>Heauens for a breath, O that it did not ſtincke.</l>
               <l>Didſt thou but ſee with what facilitie</l>
               <l>Shee winnes a louer with an amorous looke,</l>
               <l>Thou'dſt conſecrate to all eternitie</l>
               <l>Her famous name, within ſome braſen booke.</l>
               <l>Lightning of Nature, beauties amazing thunder,</l>
               <l>The rogue doth ſmile, t'would make your worſhippe wonder.</l>
               <l>Compared to her priceles-valued minde,</l>
               <l>Perfections richeſt jewell is but poore,</l>
               <l>One cannot wiſh a wench to be more kind,</l>
               <l>Miſtake me not for a Pandor, her a whore:</l>
               <l>For if you doe, you wrong vs not a little,</l>
               <l>You may know we are honeſt, cauſe we liue at Spittle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>MY Ladie's ſicke, no earthly thing can cure her,</l>
               <l>Shee lookes ſo grimme, no creature can endure her,</l>
               <l>O fetch no Doctors, t'were but idle coſt,</l>
               <l>Her boxe, <hi>pomatum,</hi> life, and all, are loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>SEeke not to comfort me, my wife is dead,</l>
               <l>Guſh forth ſalt tears, drown euery ſence with weeping,</l>
               <l>Laſt night I was ſo troubled in my bedde,</l>
               <l>That for my life, I could not wake for ſleeping:</l>
               <l>Nor can I ſtand for leaping, weepe for wincking,</l>
               <l>Nor hardly eate a bit of bread for drinking.</l>
               <l>Thus in moſt pittious manner haue I liu'd,</l>
               <l>This too too tedious time, two daies with my maid,</l>
               <l>Neuer like me was any creature grieu'd,</l>
               <l>Ere ſince her death, for very woe I haue plaid:</l>
               <l>No maruell, for I could not worke for ſweating,</l>
               <l>Nor could the egges be butterd ere I was eating.</l>
               <l>Yet now at laſt, it's time, it's time, adue,</l>
               <l>Liue (loued ſoule) for euer in ſweet bliſſe:</l>
               <l>When the old is gone, t'is time to ſeeke a new,</l>
               <l>I loue thee deerely <hi>(Beſſe)</hi> aye by this kiſſe;</l>
               <l>The match is made, and here's an end of ſorrow,</l>
               <l>Wee'l lie together to night, marrie to morrowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>HEr niceneſſe pleaſure is to walke,</l>
               <l>Roome there for Madam <hi>Minx,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O fie vpon this bawdie talke,</l>
               <l>Now faugh, by giſſe it ſtinkes.</l>
               <l>Why will you not giue place (ſir knaue)</l>
               <l>He'l not attend your fables,</l>
               <l>Shee loues not to heare of, nor to haue</l>
               <l>Such fowle euill fauour'd bables.</l>
               <l>O touch her not, for <hi>Dian's</hi> ſake,</l>
               <l>Shee's <hi>Venus</hi> chiefeſt ſcorner,</l>
               <l>The place you greatly doe miſtake,</l>
               <l>I hope this is no corner.</l>
               <l>One ſnatcht her keyes that ſate her neere,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the chaine was gawdie,</l>
               <l>And put them I'le not tell you where,</l>
               <l>Becauſe t is ſomwhat bawdie.</l>
               <l>Polluted things, touch not her rings,</l>
               <l>Your ſtinking heat ſhee'l coole:</l>
               <l>For fingers twaine, ſcarce toucht the chaine,</l>
               <l>And carri'd them to a poole,</l>
               <l>Where till ſhee had beſtowed great ſtore</l>
               <l>Of waſhing the defiled,</l>
               <l>Shee to her keyes a crowne before,</l>
               <l>Could not haue reconciled:</l>
               <l>But happieſt men croſſes endure,</l>
               <l>When Fate her might aduances,</l>
               <l>Nor puritaniſme is ſecure.</l>
               <l>From greateſt of miſchances.</l>
               <l>For within a month, and twenty daies,</l>
               <l>This <hi>Minx</hi> ſurnam'd the Milde,</l>
               <l>Did make the fowler of her keyes,</l>
               <l>The father of a childe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>SCud coward valour, flie my tempeſtuous ire</l>
               <l>And the turbouſe tumbling of my whirlewinde fury,</l>
               <l>So raging ſpleene, belke out thy ſparkling fire,</l>
               <l>My hands are iudges, and my ſword's the Iury:</l>
               <l>None ſcapes with leſſe, that dares approch my ſight,</l>
               <l>Than condemnation to eternall night.</l>
               <l>The extreame torture of his fatall houre,</l>
               <l>Attends the villaine that's next obuious,</l>
               <l>Stretch out my legs, Ile walke fiue mile an houre,</l>
               <l>Soft, now I know, what makes me ſo outragious:</l>
               <l>Knew I who would truſt me, I'de goe eaſe my minde,</l>
               <l>I am hudge and hungrie cauſe I haue not din'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>MOngſt liquids, R. and L. ſurpaſſe the reſt,</l>
               <l>Of conſonants, S. X. were, and are beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O Harke my Miſtreſſe comes, where ſhall I hide me</l>
               <l>Her ratling ſilkes prognoſticate ſhee'l chide me.</l>
               <l>This peeuiſh dreaming whore, where is ſhe miſing?</l>
               <l>That doth ſo well attend me whilſt I am riſing,</l>
               <l>No cuſsion for my feete, no chaire to ſit in,</l>
               <l>Nor any baſon ſet (forſooth) to ſpit in,</l>
               <l>A haire lay on my ſtockinges, doe you ginne to crie?</l>
               <l>Nay more (you queane) my buske-points ſtood awry,</l>
               <l>My ſhooes an inch aſunder, with no ſockes in,</l>
               <l>My kirtle wrinckled bigge as any pinne,</l>
               <l>Pox on your fingers, are they growne ſo niſe,</l>
               <l>My girdle truſt me, was as cold as iſe,</l>
               <l>Whether runne you (ſirrogue) what are you blind?</l>
               <l>I hold my life, my munkey hath not dinde:</l>
               <l>Come, dood a, dood a, this villaine muſt be beaten,</l>
               <l>This ſilly worme no bit to day hath eaten,</l>
               <l>O God is this a life? iudge (Gentlemen)</l>
               <l>A Gentleumans Monkey faſt till ten,</l>
               <l>With that vnto the trembling boy ſhe skips,</l>
               <l>And ſet's her ſignet ſeales vpon his lips,</l>
               <l>And alſo with the maide ſhee kindly dealde,</l>
               <l>Who could not paſſe in law till ſhee was ſealde,</l>
               <l>Admire the riſing of this curious charmer,</l>
               <l>Her father is ſo poore a countrie farmer,</l>
               <l>That in my conſcience t'would content his mind,</l>
               <l>To eate the ſcrappes her munkey leaues behind,</l>
               <l>Farmer? (poore man) ay, and with care obſerues</l>
               <l>To farme the ſtable as occaſion ſerues</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GEorge</hi> hath a wife which for his dagger cares not,</l>
               <l>Cauſe ſhe dares fight when <hi>Georges</hi> dagger dares not:</l>
               <l>For when he fell at ſtrawes, and leapt ore ſtockes,</l>
               <l>Courſing the can vntil he had catcht a foxe;</l>
               <l>She with her nailes examinde ſo the matter,</l>
               <l>That he was faine to draw his dagger at her,</l>
               <l>But yet poore <hi>Nouerint</hi> conquerde by the cup,</l>
               <l>Being ſoundly bangde he ſheathde his dagger vp.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MIſſa</hi> will needſly marry with a foole.</l>
               <l>her reaſon;</l>
               <l>O ſir, becauſe he hath an exlent—</l>
               <l>peace, treaſon:</l>
               <l>And reaſons moe, the maid doth ſhow,</l>
               <l>of perfect approbation,</l>
               <l>Witnes my eare that heard her ſweare,</l>
               <l>it was the Ladies faſhion.</l>
               <l>An other reaſon that doth moue her take him,</l>
               <l>I will vnfould,</l>
               <l>Becauſe (forſooth) ſhe doth intend to make him</l>
               <l>a—</l>
               <l>Your niceſt dames, that dwell by Thames,</l>
               <l>of fooles are nothing ſcorning:</l>
               <l>For the verieſt clowne in all the towne,</l>
               <l>will beſt endure the horning.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TOm</hi> had a peny but he had no purſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> then a purſe eſteemb'd, a peny worſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> grew in choler, and gan ſweare and curſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> ſould his peny and did buy a purſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> was a foole, becauſe in ſummes diſburſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Toms</hi> peny is more currant then his purſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TOm</hi> waxed thirſty, and went to his brother</l>
               <l>His purſe and belly emptie each as other:</l>
               <l>His brother kept an honeſt alehouſe neare,</l>
               <l>Sould exlent bottle ale and double beare,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Tom</hi> came there he merily gan fawne,</l>
               <l>And for a pot would put his purſe to pawne,</l>
               <l>To ſell for purſes his brother had not any,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> might haue had a pot now for his peny.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Tom</hi> was wiſe, pence haue too ſpeedy vent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> hath his purſe, his peny had beene ſpent,</l>
               <l>And now if any peny <hi>Tom</hi> can winne,</l>
               <l>Tom hath a purſe to put his peny in,</l>
               <l>But now let <hi>Tom</hi> his purſe and peny reſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom's</hi> good, his purſe is better, his peny's beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>COme (goſſippe) ſit and talke, looke there's a ſtoole</l>
               <l>Ile tell you a wonder, <hi>Prudence</hi> is a foole,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will</hi> wooes, nay woode her, did, nay would (to be ſhort)</l>
               <l>For hee askt, ſhe anſwearde no, and loſt the ſport,</l>
               <l>He askt againe (O willing wretch) ſhe would not</l>
               <l>But ſtrait ſhe wilde, he nilde, ſhe would, he could not.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>LOoke (Ladies) here's a face, for Gods ſake turne you,</l>
               <l>Pack he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hacht houſes) or good faith twil burn you</l>
               <l>So ſet with carbuncle, ruby and pearle,</l>
               <l>T'might well beſeeme the wearing of an earle,</l>
               <l>A noſe touching his mouth (which euer gapes)</l>
               <l>Which cruſht yeeldes liquor like a bunch of grapes,</l>
               <l>A chinne as free from beard as any dogge,</l>
               <l>Saue ſtubbes more hard then briſles of a hogge:</l>
               <l>And yet thereof the owner is ſo niſe,</l>
               <l>No weeke eſcapes it without ſhauing twiſe,</l>
               <l>O cry you mercy, now the cauſe I haue learnde</l>
               <l>He feares leſt by his noſe, it ſhould be burnde,</l>
               <l>Why ſay it ſhould, the courſe were not ſo deare,</l>
               <l>T'would ſaue him forty ſhillinges euery yeare,</l>
               <l>Ay, but therein another danger lies,</l>
               <l>His burning beard might burne out both his eyes.</l>
               <l>And that's the cauſe his ſhauing courſe is ſuch,</l>
               <l>Such ſcuruy faces muſt they coſt ſo much.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>A Monied foole, is like a woman witty,</l>
               <l>Neither of either knowing the right vſe</l>
               <l>Should no dies riſe, wantons grow wiſe? t'were pitty,</l>
               <l>If one, of one, if both t'weare both's abuſe,</l>
               <l>He would be miſerable of his money,</l>
               <l>Shee prodigall of wit, if ſhe had any,</l>
               <l>He like a ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et perfume in ſtinking ſhrowde,</l>
               <l>Shee like one Sunne-ſhine added to another,</l>
               <l>Hee'd be too ſlauiſh baſe, ſhee too too proud,</l>
               <l>The flame would burne her's out, the ſmoake his ſmother</l>
               <l>But this conuerſion ſeemes to me the bonieſt.</l>
               <l>Let him be wiſe and rich, ſhe onely honeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>FLaminio's</hi> chinne ſcornes euery cut but bare,</l>
               <l>And yet his head ſcornes nought, ſaue onely haire.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>TI's merry when goſſips ſit vpon a bench,</l>
               <l>To talke of riſting <hi>Robbin</hi> and his wench,</l>
               <l>Of faire <hi>Philip</hi> and of <hi>Beſſe</hi> the browne,</l>
               <l>And euery <hi>Ducke</hi> and <hi>Broodgooſe</hi> in the towne,</l>
               <l>My henne, ſaieth one, each weeke ſeuen egges doth lay,</l>
               <l>What's that? quoth another, mine laies two euery day,</l>
               <l>The third complaines, ſhe broke her hatchil handels,</l>
               <l>The fourth hatt the Ouen, the fift made candels,</l>
               <l>The ſixt beganne to ſneuill, ſnore and ſneeſe,</l>
               <l>The ſeuenth on fryday made a morninges cheeſe,</l>
               <l>By this; confuſed babling all doth ſmother,</l>
               <l>The lyes are loſt, one cannot heare another,</l>
               <l>Strait all fall out, bout fathering of a fart,</l>
               <l>They riſe, and ſcold, and ſcrach, and ſo depart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Countrie fellow courſer cloth'd then witted,</l>
               <l>A fooliſh Lawyer wiſely thus hee fitted;</l>
               <l>Good ſir (quoth he) are you neceſſitie,</l>
               <l>The Lawyer was amaſde exceedingly,</l>
               <l>And askte him why neceſſitie? (ſir Daw)</l>
               <l>Forſooth (quoth he) becauſe you haue no law.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>SVſinne's</hi> all mettle, onely aire and fire,</l>
               <l>A wench as merry as one would deſire.</l>
               <l>She'l looke, ſhe'l laugh, ſhe'l dance, ſhe'l play, ſhe'l ſing,</l>
               <l>She'l clippe, ſhe'l kiſſe, nay ſhe'l doe any thing,</l>
               <l>With any one at cardes ſhe'l haue a ſay,</l>
               <l>And laugh and lie downe, is her common play</l>
               <l>She playes at tables wel, and true as any,</l>
               <l>Onely ſometimes ſhe'l beare a man too many:</l>
               <l>At bowles ſhe beates your cheefeſt alley-lubbers,</l>
               <l>Alwaies prouided that they hold out rubbers;</l>
               <l>Nay, if you'l nocke the ſhafte, ſhe'l ſhoote at prickes,</l>
               <l>She's nothing elſe but mirth and <hi>meretrix.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>RObbin</hi> doth riſe, and forth muſt needeſly goe,</l>
               <l>Onely to ſpeake but with a friend, or ſo,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Robbin's</hi> wit in wetting's euer ſhrunke,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Robbin</hi> neare comes home, but <hi>Robbin's</hi> drunke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WIll you not pledge me ſir? now by this light,</l>
               <l>I care not of a bul ruſh if I fight:</l>
               <l>Nay now my reſolution naught withſtands,</l>
               <l>Horror and blood attend my murdrous hands:</l>
               <l>Intreats are vaine, for when I once am willing,</l>
               <l>The world cannot diſſwade my blade from killing.</l>
               <l>He draw'd, and winckt, and thruſt and ſhak't, &amp; ſwore,</l>
               <l>And kept him off his rapiers length and more;</l>
               <l>Well plaid in faith, maſſe that had ſpoild your ſport,</l>
               <l>Had it not beene at leaſt a yard too ſhort.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bullie,</hi> put vp, I ſee thou art a man,</l>
               <l>Come <hi>Tom,</hi> by Chriſt, Ile giue thee halfe a Canne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Face, no face, hath our <hi>Theophiles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But the right forme of <hi>Mephoſtophiles:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I know t'would ſerue, and yet I am no wizard,</l>
               <l>To playe the Diuel in'th Vault without a vizard;</l>
               <l>(Nature) be it ſpoke to thy eternall grace,</l>
               <l>That a man hath mettle euen in's very face.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:17"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>NIcke</hi> weares three noſes in an vnion,</l>
               <l>Each richly died with skarlet of the beſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nichol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> refuſed the Communion,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the parſon praied not for his ſmel-feaſt:</l>
               <l>He onely praied for triple-noſed <hi>Nicke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now <hi>Nicke</hi> was well, but's noſe was hugely ſicke.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicke</hi> plaies at tables well; but O his noſes!</l>
               <l>For with his eies, the worme-eate ſlaues play bootie:</l>
               <l>His lucke in caſting's good; yet ſtill he loſes:</l>
               <l>How can he chooſe, when's things are ſo vnſutie?</l>
               <l>For his fellow gamſter makes his ſincke a ſice,</l>
               <l>Whilſt he remooues his noſe to ſee the dice.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:17"/>
            <lg>
               <l>THe great diſpencer of ſmall conſcience,</l>
               <l>Hath made his niggard-name moſt richly knowne,</l>
               <l>His money-thirſting ſoule, that conſcious <hi>ens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is ſure the diuels, though his coyne's his owne:</l>
               <l>How doth that chuile abuſe his pyles of pelfe,</l>
               <l>That worſe then any diuell damnes himſelfe.</l>
               <l>Reply not <hi>(Chance)</hi> though I call thee inceſtuous whore,</l>
               <l>Bringing forth golden baſtards to thy ſonne,</l>
               <l>To him that hath too much, ſtill giuing more,</l>
               <l>And yet his auarice hath neuer done.</l>
               <l>You muſt be pleas'd with what I ſaid before,</l>
               <l>For our ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> can prooue you are a whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Doe you ſee yon Munkie in the ſilken hat,</l>
               <l>His cloake of veluet, and his Ierkin leather,</l>
               <l>May't pleaſe your worſhip heare the coxcombe chat,</l>
               <l>And ſee him draw his mouth and eies together:</l>
               <l>So impudently bold, that none can feare him,</l>
               <l>And ſweares and lies, t'would doe you good to heare him.</l>
               <l>He hath left his reformation now of lockes,</l>
               <l>How thinke you then his liuing doth come in?</l>
               <l>Why he mends the burning feauer, cures the poxe,</l>
               <l>And gets his liuing by the peoples ſinne:</l>
               <l>Good his head hath, and Rich his heele doth craue,</l>
               <l>Rich if you will, but good? in troth he's a knaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>IF he's no ſlaue, that to all vice is thrall,</l>
               <l>Begges ierkins, hats, hoſe, dublets, the diuell and all:</l>
               <l>And of no man of Note, but ſtill doth craue;</l>
               <l>Why then <hi>praedictus Mounſieur</hi> is no ſlaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>FOrbeare (impure) ſtaine not her thought cleare name,</l>
               <l>The ſaint's deuoted to the Queene of ſhame:</l>
               <l>Moſt beaſtly-wicked, man packe ſpeedy hence,</l>
               <l>O God, come hether with vnchaſt pretence,</l>
               <l>Wrinckle (alluring face) eies, wanton, niſe,</l>
               <l>Come, come, ile ſcrach you out, muſt you entiſe?</l>
               <l>Strait to her maid the gallant doth deliuer</l>
               <l>A ſatten gowne, which he had bought to giue her,</l>
               <l>Which ſhe eſpying, thus endes her churliſh frowne;</l>
               <l>Buſſe me <hi>(Ducke)</hi> ſweet, who'd haue thought, thou hadſt had a gown?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>CRambde be the guts of begger ſlaues with mutton,</l>
               <l>And greaſie licking of the dripping panne:</l>
               <l>I care not for ſuch groſſe meates of a button,</l>
               <l>Giue me a Capon. Zoundes a man's a man:</l>
               <l>Muſt Gallants ſtand like puſſe-cats crying mew?</l>
               <l>Drink (villains) why ground, I hope you wil look blue</l>
               <l>Attend vs (rogues) Vintner, bring heer your wife</l>
               <l>And ſhift her, <hi>(ſirra)</hi> in her ſatten gowne,</l>
               <l>What is thy Ordinary? now by <hi>Pharoes</hi> life,</l>
               <l>Ile leaue it, if't be vnder halfe a crowne.</l>
               <l>Ti's but two ſhillinges: O extreame diſgrace,</l>
               <l>He ſcornes to ſuppe, when ſuppers grow ſo baſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat ailes (my <hi>Fiſco</hi>), prethee (chucke) be merry,</l>
               <l>Thy ſadnes makes my ſorow paſſe all boundes:</l>
               <l>Come Buſſe thy Miſtreſſe, is my puppy weary?</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Aquavitae</hi> quickly <hi>Fiſco</hi> ſoundes,</l>
               <l>I faint with griefe, O beare me to my bed,</l>
               <l>The paragon of fiſting dogs is dead.</l>
               <l>Then to an Epitaph my ſelfe ile taske,</l>
               <l>And thus in braſen letters be it written,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fiſco</hi> loude butter, and did die of'th laske,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a prety dogge, O death too ſhitten,</l>
               <l>Now all you mourning curres in griefe perſeuere,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Fiſcoes</hi> fifting may be famous euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>BIfronted <hi>Peter's</hi> head, growne bigge with wife,</l>
               <l>Yet a loues her whoreſhippe as he loues his life,</l>
               <l>Ay, <hi>(Peter)</hi> winke at ſmall faultes for thy wench</l>
               <l>Hath a pocky ſort of crownes, all onely French.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat giue ten pound for counſell? giue a ſtraw,</l>
               <l>Do you think ther's any ſo baſely-low priſd law?</l>
               <l>Well, yet ile take it, and ſomewhat I will doe,</l>
               <l>But t'will not be aboue a word or two,</l>
               <l>So foule a caſe as this hath neuer paſt,</l>
               <l>Nay, I am as ſure as can be, you'l be caſt:</l>
               <l>With that the diſcontented Client frownes,</l>
               <l>And makes a ruſling conſort mongſt his crownes,</l>
               <l>The which no ſooner (laugh not) Conſcience heares,</l>
               <l>But preſently the caſe is changde, he ſweares,</l>
               <l>Pardon me (ſir) I did miſtake the courſe,</l>
               <l>Aſſure your ſelfe, the land is firmely yours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I Know <hi>Ann Hill,</hi> and yet it is not <hi>mons,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both ſpringde, and bridgde, with neither <hi>ſons</hi> nor <hi>pons:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This <hi>Hill</hi> hath a wil, O ſtrange, a <hi>Hill</hi> a will!</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>fons, pons, mons,</hi> yet ſpring, bridge, yea <hi>Ann Hill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ay, <hi>(Hill)</hi> leaue thy will, or elſe <hi>(wil)</hi> leaue thy <hi>Hill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Will</hi> with <hi>Hill,</hi> or <hi>Hil</hi> with <hi>Will,</hi> doth ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>RIchard</hi> and <hi>Robert</hi> with intent to gull them,</l>
               <l>Borrowed of <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Wat</hi> a hundred pound,</l>
               <l>But marke how finely <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Wat</hi> did pull them:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Wat</hi> was wit, and <hi>Will</hi> was wily found:</l>
               <l>They ſaid themſelues had not to eaſe their ſorrow,</l>
               <l>but if they'd bring a pawne, they would it borrow.</l>
               <l>They pawnde a leaſe of threeſcore poundes a yeare,</l>
               <l>Thinking to get it backe againe by craft,</l>
               <l>For not long after, both come backe and ſweare,</l>
               <l>They are in ſute of law, and needes muſt haue't.</l>
               <l>For if it be not ſhowne within three howres,</l>
               <l>Tis loſt (quoth they) and then nor yours nor ours.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wat</hi> laught at this, and <hi>Wil</hi> or rather wile,</l>
               <l>With doubled Negatiues their cunning croſt,</l>
               <l>They walkt away in choller, and meane while</l>
               <l>The time of pay was paſt, the leaſe was loſt.</l>
               <l>Thus were theſe crowes guld by the other dawes,</l>
               <l>But <hi>fallere fallentes non est fraus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>OBſerue the ponderous ſenſe of euery word:</l>
               <l>And looke you heer's a face for any Lord:</l>
               <l>Doeſt ſee this beard? I tell thee (groome) each haire,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Preſter Iohn</hi> his crowne, I prize more deare,</l>
               <l>Note but my carriage, thou ſeeſt I am moſt valiant,</l>
               <l>Then iudge if I am not a perfect gallant:</l>
               <l>He learnde coniunction when he went to ſchoole,</l>
               <l>For wordes, face, beard, behauiour, al's but foole.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAt</hi> grewe of late moſt miſerable poore,</l>
               <l>But of his vncle he was ſure of helpe,</l>
               <l>And comming to his houſe, knockt at the doore,</l>
               <l>But marke the curriſh nature of this whelpe:</l>
               <l>He knew him not, nor bade him once come in,</l>
               <l>Knowing torne breeches could not be his kinne.</l>
               <l>But neuer-alwaies-bad-imperious fortune</l>
               <l>Rais'd his deſerts ſoone from thridbare to braue,</l>
               <l>When loe, this worme-eate Churle, ſeemes to importune</l>
               <l>The lou'd acquaintance of his Cuzze to haue:</l>
               <l>VVhat incantation this prowd world bewitches,</l>
               <l>VVhen men are leſſe eſteemb'd, then veluet breeches.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MIca</hi> is turnd religious: why? he faſteth</l>
               <l>Long as his pennileſſe religion laſteth.</l>
               <l>A poxe take <hi>Pierce,</hi> for ſince his Supplication,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Mica's</hi> purſe was nere in reparation:</l>
               <l>Goe fagget, how ſir? a ſeminarie Prieſt,</l>
               <l>VVhy I haue not any croſſe about me, ſeeſt?</l>
               <l>VVhich croſleſſe croſſe, made <hi>Mica's</hi> caſe ſo cleare,</l>
               <l>And therefore faire fall nothing once a yeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat's he that walkes with ſuch a ſtately grace,</l>
               <l>And puts downe any Coach-horſe for a pace:</l>
               <l>With a hat as long, and ſharpe, as the Dutch ſteeple,</l>
               <l>Able to feare ten groates worth of poore people:</l>
               <l>Who his muſtachoes ſo aſcendent weares,</l>
               <l>They ſeeme to whiſper rebellion in his eares:</l>
               <l>VVith a noſe, in circuit like a new chang'd moone,</l>
               <l>And for a face, puts downe your beſt Baboone.</l>
               <l>VVith rapier by his ſide, halfe a yard more</l>
               <l>Than would meaſure Prick-markes off at halfe a ſcore?</l>
               <l>VVhy doe you aske? cauſe I may ſay to you,</l>
               <l>I heard one ſweare, that fellow was neuer true:</l>
               <l>Hee'l make a match to day, and firmely ſpeake it,</l>
               <l>Nay ſweare, to morrow, forſweare, the third day break it.</l>
               <l>Nay more; he ſaid he was tyranys chiefe iewell,</l>
               <l>No Turke, no Pagan, no wild Boare ſo cruell:</l>
               <l>He was naught, nay worſe, he neuer meanes to mend;</l>
               <l>Hee'd gull, deceiue, nay more, hee'd rob his friend:</l>
               <l>To ſay what country man he is, t'is hard,</l>
               <l>It is indeed: for I thinke he is no—</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WHo'd thinke yon gallant by the boy attended</l>
               <l>Did lie a bed, mean while his hoſe were mended?</l>
               <l>Or that they liu'd hid in a hiue like Bees,</l>
               <l>Onely with barley bread, and <hi>Bridgenorth</hi> cheeſe?</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall you heare him, and his boy proteſt,</l>
               <l>That Beefe and Mutton's but a skuruie feaſt:</l>
               <l>He skornes to feed at night, on gooſe, or ducke,</l>
               <l>Yet (Fortune) I perceiue that you haue ſtucke</l>
               <l>Vpon his wittie nap, your wealthy burre,</l>
               <l>For in wit, he's farre; and yet in wealth, he's <hi>fur.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>MY miſtreſſe loftines, who i'th light doth marke,</l>
               <l>Thinkes not ſhee'd be ſo lowly in the darke,</l>
               <l>There (proſtrate wretch) doue-like, deuoid of gaull,</l>
               <l>How long ſo ere the wrong, ſhee puts vp all.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>(Wat)</hi> your iealouſie with you plaies bootie,</l>
               <l>When you come home, I hope ſhe doe's her dutie.</l>
               <l>To clip, and coll, and kiſſe, ſhee neuer miſſes,</l>
               <l>What? cannot husbands be content with kiſſes?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:22"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faſingo</hi> hath a backe, iſt poſsible?</l>
               <l>Aye, and a bellie, but as vnſociable</l>
               <l>As any backe, and belly you ſhall finde,</l>
               <l>For's backe goes braue, marry his bellie's pin'd:</l>
               <l>His backe weares ſilke,</l>
               <l>His belly ſcornes milke,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he cannot get it:</l>
               <l>But if he can robbe</l>
               <l>A Herring of a cobbe,</l>
               <l>You'd bleſſe you to ſee him eate it.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faſingo</hi> hath another tricke well noted,</l>
               <l>No Pilchers head eſcapes him, though vnbloted:</l>
               <l>But he cares not much for marmelet or gelly,</l>
               <l>But if a cheeſe will find parings, he'l find bellie.</l>
               <l>When any he ſeeth,</l>
               <l>Hee'l picke his teeth,</l>
               <l>As he ſits at his dore:</l>
               <l>VVhen he hath not eate,</l>
               <l>One bit of meat,</l>
               <l>In three daies ſpace before.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:22"/>
            <lg>
               <l>MY Miſtreſſe goes each day in her Scotch hat,</l>
               <l>Yet ſets me downe to ſupper with a ſprat,</l>
               <l>And walkes her ſelfe meane while about the hall,</l>
               <l>To ſee I eate both head, and taile and all,</l>
               <l>My ſwaggering ſtomacke brooks head, taile, skin &amp; bone</l>
               <l>Whip ſayes my mouth, and then the ſprat is gone,</l>
               <l>Then learnedly my Miſtreſſe gins to chat,</l>
               <l>The wondrous vertues of a bloted ſprat,</l>
               <l>Firſt how it fils, next how it doth reſtore</l>
               <l>One from a hundred ſickneſſes and more,</l>
               <l>But in my throat I ſcorne this phiſicke diet,</l>
               <l>Nor can my belly keepe my guts in quiet,</l>
               <l>Which ſhe perceiuing gins to ſcold outright,</l>
               <l>Bids giue me the other ſprat, and choke me quite,</l>
               <l>VVhen loe, my teeth as quicke as any cats,</l>
               <l>Soone make two ſimple fellowes of the ſprats,</l>
               <l>I thinke you'l neere haue ſupt (quoth ſhe) ſir gull,</l>
               <l>I riſe, ſhe ſaies, I hope you are farting full,</l>
               <l>Ti's true, with aire, therein we both accord,</l>
               <l>But to preſerue, I do beſeech the Lord,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom Weningtons</hi> blue breeches from the rats,</l>
               <l>And me, and all good men, from ſupping with ſprats.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>AN honeſt Vicker, a wiſard or a witch</l>
               <l>A Chimney-ſweeper, <hi>Tom Tinker</hi> and his bitch.</l>
               <l>Met altogether at a tipling houſe,</l>
               <l>To trie each other's valour at carouſe,</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did reaſon, the witch did alſo well,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chimny-ſweepe</hi> better, the <hi>Tincker</hi> did excell,</l>
               <l>And ſurely <hi>Tom</hi> had quickly got the beſt,</l>
               <l>But that his bitch paſt him, and all the reſt,</l>
               <l>They wondred much at <hi>Tom,</hi> but at <hi>Tib</hi> more,</l>
               <l>Faith (quoth the <hi>Vicker</hi>) ti's an exlent whore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chimny-ſweepe</hi> and the <hi>Tincker</hi> fell to fighting,</l>
               <l>Kicking grew in vſe, with pinching, ſcratching &amp; biting,</l>
               <l>The witch and the bitch fell out, and gan to brawle:</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpoke latine enough to choke them all,</l>
               <l>And neare leaues off vntill the fray he ends,</l>
               <l>Cals for the other pot, then all are friends;</l>
               <l>And then a freſh they fall againe to ſwill:</l>
               <l>But the <hi>Chimny-ſweeper</hi> takes <hi>Tobacco</hi> ſtill,</l>
               <l>Doe you aske why? O his Commiſſion's large,</l>
               <l>For he may ſweep his noſe himſelfe, and ſaue that charge</l>
               <l>And preſently the <hi>Tincker</hi> gins to ſucke it,</l>
               <l>Till he makes his chappes as blacke as any bucket,</l>
               <l>O then let Gentlemen leaue off to thinke on't:</l>
               <l>When <hi>Tinkers</hi> and ſuch raſcall ſlaues do drink on't.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>ZAy <hi>(Ziſſe)</hi> canſt fancy? then prethe conſtant proue,</l>
               <l>For in conſcience I am beaſtly deepe in loue:</l>
               <l>I be ſworne thoſe frownes will make me to abhorre thee,</l>
               <l>Come, if thou't haue me, heer's a pinne-purſe for thee,</l>
               <l>Ah Roſtemeat <hi>(Siſſe),</hi> I am ſure to me thy marriage,</l>
               <l>Would be as good or better then plumme-porrage,</l>
               <l>Sure thou't be plag'y ſweet to him ſhal trie thee,</l>
               <l>I know no butfer-milke will ere come nie thee,</l>
               <l>And furthermore <hi>Siſſe</hi> comes ſo neare to ſouſe,</l>
               <l>That I could almoſt eate my blacke-bricht mouſe,</l>
               <l>And I mongſt youthes haue euer bore the bell,</l>
               <l>Thou ſeeſt my heeles be whole, and all things well,</l>
               <l>My head and beard (as ruſty bacon) yellow,</l>
               <l>Nay I am ſure an extreame admirable fellow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Siſſe</hi> laught and let a fart, there loue was ſhowne:</l>
               <l>And runne away, iudge, is not ſhee his owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:24"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TIm</hi> ſpeaketh common, what's proper to a king,</l>
               <l>Calling for's doublet, he bids our doublet bring,</l>
               <l>VVhy ours you'l aske? O (ſir) he hath good reaſon,</l>
               <l>That our's as cleare (as he of ſhift) from treaſon:</l>
               <l>For he and's brother, <hi>freti ſimplicibus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wear'th ſute, and'th ſhirt, <hi>alternis vicibus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:24"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WHy <hi>(Will)</hi> art thou my brother? then giue mee a thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p</l>
               <l>Come bezle to me, let's be drunk in pomp:</l>
               <l>Let the Iackes grone, the Iugges be all confounded,</l>
               <l>The Cruzes cruſht, Cans crackt, Pitchers expounded:</l>
               <l>The blacke pots pincht, bowles bang'd, cups canoniz'd,</l>
               <l>The fawſets fir'd, the ſpiggots anatomiz'd:</l>
               <l>Now noſes twang, guts grone, <hi>(Will)</hi> throw thy cloake off</l>
               <l>Who'd die infamous, neuer to be ſpoke of?</l>
               <l>Shal's hawle the houſe by'th heeles out at the dores,</l>
               <l>You, hoſteſſe, bawd, come; where be all your whores?</l>
               <l>O riſe not ſpleene, by'th Lord I am offended,</l>
               <l>VVhat cannot dubbed drunkards be attended?</l>
               <l>That's skuruie ale, this ſweete, the other ſower,</l>
               <l>I haue drunke a barrell better within this hower.</l>
               <l>Rouſe off thy tipple <hi>(Will)</hi> be not afraid,</l>
               <l>They drinke, they ſtincke, hoſe, roome, and all's beraid.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Peter Potus</hi> euery morning praies,</l>
               <l>Diuelliſh, pray God not damned are his daies.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:25"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VS, ours, all, the world, the fleſh, the diuell,</l>
               <l>With wealth, luſt, craft, allures, deceiues, orecomes,</l>
               <l>Fathers, ſonnes, both, none can eſcape that euill,</l>
               <l>Which by tranſgreſsion from olde <hi>Adam</hi> comes:</l>
               <l>Yet grace, adoption, faith, pure, holy, ciuill,</l>
               <l>VVithſtands, deludes, orecomes, world, fleſh, &amp; diuell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu horrid ſinnes, that heauen hath named deadly,</l>
               <l>Ceaſe to ſuggeſt the wretched ſoules of men:</l>
               <l>You that of all the world haue made a medly,</l>
               <l>Yet now at laſt ſleepe in your helliſh denne:</l>
               <l>If not, yet be vnited; be ſeauen no more,</l>
               <l>For ſeauen are one, one worſe than ſeauen; a whore.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:19311:25"/>
            <head>Epillogus.</head>
            <l>HEre haue you read, if harſh, not triuiall ſport,</l>
            <l>T'was briefe, if bad, the time you loſt was ſhort:</l>
            <l>And yet becauſe it was the Authors firſt,</l>
            <l>Say t'is but naught, although it be the worſt.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>Reader, ſome faults (by reaſon of my abſence) eſcaped by the Printer: I intreat you, if you will, to excuſe; if not, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect: the firſt, if kind; you may: the ſecond, if curious; you muſt: and eaſily. If it bee in the ende of the verſe, by comparing the meeter: if elſe where, the ſence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
